阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@Auriance 校：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
【本期推荐阅读：《图灵的秘密：他的生平、思想及论文解读》】
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机科学速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne, and welcome to CrashCourse Computer Science!
之前几期
Over the past few episodes,
我们主要在理解计算机科学的基础
we've been building up our understanding of computer science fundamentals,
比如函数 算法和数据结构
such as functions, algorithms and data structures.
今天我们往回看
Today, we're going to take a step back and look at the person
认识现代计算理论的奠基人
who formulated many of the theoretical concepts that underline modern computation.
计算机科学之父 长得不像本尼迪克特·康伯巴奇的 艾伦·图灵
The father of computer science and not quite Benedict Cumberbatch lookalike Alan Turing.
【本尼迪克特·康伯巴奇，即“卷福”，在电影《模仿游戏》中饰演图灵】
艾伦·麦席森·图灵 1912年生于伦敦
Alan Mathison Turing was born in London in 1912
早年就在数学和科学方面展现了惊人的天赋
and showed an incredible aptitude for maths and science throughout his early education.
他与计算机科学的首次接触在1935年 当时还没有计算机科学的叫法
His first brush of what we now call computer science came in 1935
当时还是剑桥大学国王学院的硕士研究生
while he was a master's student at King's College in Cambridge.
他决定解决德国数学家大卫·希尔伯特提出的问题
He set out to solve a problem posed by German Mathematician David Hilbert
就是可判定性问题
known as the Entscheidungsproblem or decision problem, which asked the following:
它提出 是否存在一个算法能够接受以形式逻辑表述的问题
is there an algorithm that takes as input a statement written in formal logic,
并总是能正确的回答“是”或“否”
and produces a "yes" or "no" answer that's always accurate?
如果存在这样的算法 可以用它来回答问题
If such an algorithm existed, we could use it to answer questions like,
比如 “是否存在比所有数字都大的数”
"Is there a number bigger than all numbers?"
当然不存在 这个问题我们已经知道答案了
No, there's not. We know the answer to that one,
但我们还想知道其他数学问题的答案
but there are many other questions in mathematics that we'd like to know the answer to.
所以如果这种算法存在 我们想知道它
So if this algorithm existed, we'd want to know it.
美国数学家 阿伦索·丘奇于1935年首先提出了解答
The American mathematician Alonzo Church
first presented a solution to this problem in 1935.
他创造了一个数学表达系统 称为 λ演算/λ算子
He developed a system of mathematical expressions called Lambda Calculus
并证明了这种通用算法不存在
and demonstrated that no such universal algorithm could exist.
尽管λ演算可以表示任意计算
Although Lambda Calculus was capable of representing any computation,
其数学技巧既难理解又难应用
the mathematical technique was difficult to apply and understand.
大约同时期的大西洋彼岸
At pretty much the same time on the other side of the Atlantic,
艾伦·图灵独立研究出了另一种解法
Alan Turing came up with his own approach to solve the decision problem.
他提出了一个理想化计算装置 现在称为图灵机
He proposed a hypothetical computing machine, which we now call a Turing Machine.
图灵机是一种计算数学模型 简单但功能强大
Turing Machines provided a simple, yet powerful mathematical model of computation.
尽管基于完全不同的数学理论
Although using totally different mathematics,
图灵机在计算能力上与λ演算是等价的
they were functionally equivalent to lambda calculus in terms of their computational power.
因为相对更简单
However their relative simplicity made them much more popular
它在新兴的计算机科学领域更流行
in the burgeoning field of computer science.
它真的很简单 马上我就讲
In fact, they're simple enough that I'm going to explain it right now.
图灵机是一种理想化的计算装置
A Turing Machine is a theoretical computing device
使用无限长度的内存纸带存储符号
equipped with an infinitely long memory tape which stores symbols
和一个读写头
and a device called a read/write head
读写头能读取 写入 或者修改纸带上的符号
which can read and write, or modify, symbols on that tape.
还有一个状态变量
There's also a state variable in which
它保存机器的当前状态
we can hold a piece of information about the current state of the machine.
以及一组规则 说明机器能做什么
And a set of rules that describes what the machine does.
当机器状态和当前读取的符号确定时
Given a state and the current symbol the head is reading,
机器根据规则可以在纸带上写入新符号 改变机器状态
the rule can be to write a symbol on the tape change the state of the machine
将读写头左/右移动一格
move the read/write head to the left or right by one spot
或是以上的任意组合
or any combination of these actions.
为了便于理解 我们来看个例子
To make this concrete let's work through a simple example:
图灵机以字符串形式 读取一个末尾是0的二进制数
a Turing Machine that reads a string of ones ending in a zero
然后计算这个二进制数是否包含偶数个"1"
and computes whether there is an even number of ones.
如果是 那么机器在纸带上写"1"  否则写"0"
If that's true, the machine will write a one to the tape and if it's false, it'll write a zero.
首先需要确定图灵机的规则
First we need to define our Turing machine rules.
如果状态为偶 且 纸带的当前符号为1
If the state is even and the current symbol of the tape is one,
我们就更新图灵机的状态为奇 右移读写头
then we update the machine state to odd and move the head to the right.
反之 如果状态为偶 且 当前符号为0
On the other hand if the state is even and the current symbol is zero,
这说明已经到了字符串的末尾
which means we've reached the end of the string of ones,
我们在纸带上写1 并将 图灵机状态写为停止
then we write one to the tape and change the state to halt,
这样图灵机就完成了计算
as in we're finished and the Turing machine has completed the computation.
我们还需要奇状态下的图灵机规则
We also need rules for when the Turing machine is in an odd state,
一个对应纸带上符号为0 另一个对应符号为1
one rule for the symbol on the tape is a zero and another for when it is one.
最后还需要定义一个起始状态 我们会设为偶状态
Lastly we need to define a starting state, which we'll set to be even.
这样就完成了图灵机起始状态的所有规则
Now we've defined the rules in the starting state of our Turing machine,
这和计算机程序很类似 我们用测试输入来运行一下
which is comparable to a computer program, we can run it on some example input.
假设我们在纸带上存储了 1 1 0
Let's say we store 1 1 0 onto tape.
2个1意味着有偶数个1
That's two ones which means there is an even number of ones,
如果还不熟悉这个概念 我们也许应该学一下数学速成课
and if that's news to you, we should probably get working on crash course Math.
目前所有的规则只是让读写头右移
Notice that our rules only ever move their head to the right
所以不涉及(读写头)左侧的纸带
so the rest of the tape is irrelevant.
为了简化 我们假设这部分的值都为空
We'll leave it blank for simplicity.
图灵机可以运行了 我们来运行吧
Our Turing machine is all ready to go so let's start it.
状态是偶 并且 第一个数是1
Our state is even and the first number we see is a one.
匹配第一条规则 于是我们开始执行
That matches our topmost rule and so we execute the effect,
将状态改为奇 同时 将读写头右移一个单位
which is to update the state to odd and move the read/write head to the right by one spot.
好了 现在我们看到了纸带上的另一个1 但现在状态为奇
Okay, now we see another one on the tape, but this time our state is odd
所于是执行第三条规则
and so we execute our third rule
将状态又改回偶 再右移读写头
which sets the state back to even and moves the head to the right.
现在读到了0 并且当前状态为偶 所以我们执行第二条规则
Now we see a 0 and our current state is even so we execute our second rule
向纸带上写1 表示真
which is to write a 1 to the tape signifying that yes, it's true,
字符串中有偶数个1 机器停止运行
there is an even number of ones, and finally the machine halts.
这就是图灵机的原理。很简单对吧
That's how Turing machines work. Pretty simple right?
你可能会想知道为什么它这么重要
so you might be wondering why they're such a big deal.
图灵证明了图灵机可以执行任意运算
Well Turing shows that this simple hypothetical machine can perform any computation
只要有足够的时间和存储空间
if given enough time and memory
图灵机是一个通用计算机
It's a general-purpose computer.
刚才的例子很简单
Our program was a simple example,
但只要状态和纸带足够多 你可以构建任何东西
but with enough Rules states and tape you could build anything-
浏览器 魔兽世界 随便什么
a web browser, world of warcraft - whatever!
当然它效率低的可怕 但理论上确实可行
Of course it would be ridiculously inefficient, but it is theoretically possible.
所以作为计算模型 图灵机的理念如此重要
And that's why, as a model of computing, it's such a powerful idea.
实际上 仅考虑计算的适用领域
In fact in terms of what it can and cannot compute
图灵机是最强大的计算机
there's no computer more powerful than a Turing machine.
具备这样能力的计算机 我们称它为图灵完备的
A computer that is as powerful is called Turing complete.
任何现代计算系统 笔记本 智能手机
Every modern computing system your laptop your smartphone
甚至微波炉和温度计里的微电脑都是图灵完备的
and even the little computer inside your microwave and thermostat are all Turing Complete.
为了解答希尔伯特的可判定性问题
To answer Hilbert's decision problem,
图灵在一个有趣的计算难题中引入了图灵机
Turing applied these new Turing machines to an intriguing computational puzzle:
即 停机问题
the halting problem.
简单说就是 是否存在一种算法
Put simply this asks "Is there an algorithm that can determine,
在给定一台图灵机和纸带输入的情况下
given a description of a Turing machine and the input from its tape,
能够判定这台机器会最终停止运行
whether the Machine will run forever or halt?"
举个例子 我们知道当输入1 1 0时 图灵机会停止
For example we know our Turing machine will halt when given the input 1 1 0,
因为我们一步步执行程序 直到机器停止
because we literally walk through the example until it halted,
但对更复杂的问题呢
but what about a more complex problem?
有办法不运行也能知道结果吗
Is there a way to figure out if the program will halt without executing it?
有些程序可能会运行数年之久 如果能提前知道结果会很有用
Some programs might take years to run so it would be useful to know before we run it
而不是运行之后苦苦等待结果
and wait and wait and wait and then start getting worried and wonder
直到几十年过去 两鬓斑白 再悲伤的重启程序
and then decades later when you're old and gray control-alt-delete so much sadness.
但很遗憾
Unfortunately Turing came up with a proof that shows
图灵证明了停机问题不可解
the halting problem was in fact unsolvable,
证明用了一个巧妙的逻辑悖论
through a clever logical contradiction.
我们一起看看证明过程
Let's Follow his reasoning.
假设我们有一台图灵机
Imagine we have a hypothetical Turing machine
已经加载了一个程序和纸带输入
that takes a description of a program and some input for his tape
它要么输出Yes后停机，要么输出no继续运行
and always outputs either Yes, it halts or no, it doesn't
我给它取个名字Holtz 简称H
and I'm going to give this machine a fun name H for Holtz.
不用考虑它的原理
Don't worry about how it works.
就假设存在这样的机器 只考虑理论
Let's just assume such a machine exists We're talking theory here.
图灵分析说 如果存在一个程序 H无法计算它的停机状态
Turing reasoned if there existed a program whose halting behavior was not decidable by H
这就意味着停机问题无解
it would mean the halting problem is unsolvable
为了求解 图灵设计了另一个以H为基础的图灵机
To find one Turing designed another Turing machine that built on top of H.
如果H说程序停止 那么新机器会一直运行
If H says the program holds, then we'll make our new machine loop forever.
否则 新机器停止并输出no
If the answer is no, it doesn't halt, we'll have the new machine output a no and halt.
简单说就是 新机器与H的行为相反
In essence we're building a machine that does the opposite of what H says:
如果程序一直运行 那么新机器停止 反之则新机器一直运行
halt if the program doesn't halt and run forever if the program halts.
我们还需要在新机器上增加一个分离器
For this argument we'll also need to add a splitter to the front of our new machine
这样机器只有一个输入 再将输入作为H的程序和输入
so that it accepts only one input and passes that as both the program and input into H.
给新机器取个名字 叫Bizarro
Let's call this new machine "Bizzaro".
目前为止一切还说得过去 是吗
So far this seems like a plausible machine, right?
马上要变复杂了 再等等
Now it's going to get pretty complicated. But bear with me for a second.
看看把Bizzaro自身的输出当作它的输入后会发生什么
Look what happens when you pass Bizzaro a description of itself as the input.
这相当于问H Bizzaro会怎么样
This means we're asking H what Bizzaro will do when asked to evaluate itself.
但如果H说Bizzaro停机 随后Bizzaro就开始无限循环
But if H says Bizzaro halts then Bizzaro enters its infinite loop and thus doesn't halt.
如果H说Bizzaro不会停机 随后Bizzaro输出no并且停机
And if H says Bizarro doesn't halt then Bizzaro outputs a no and halts.
所以H不能解决停机问题因为这个问题无解
So H can't possibly decide the halting problem correctly because there is no answer.
这是一个悖论
It's a paradox  and this paradox means that
意味折图灵机无法解决停机问题
the halting problem cannot be solved with Turing machines.
记住图灵证明了图灵机可以完成任意运算
Remember Turing proved that Turing machines could implement any computation
所以停机问题的结果证明了
so this solution to the halting problem proves
计算无法解决所有问题
that not all problems can be solved by computation.
哈哈 太难了 我自己可能要再看一遍
Wow, that's some heavy stuff I might have to watch that again myself.
简而言之 丘奇和图灵证明了计算机能力的局限
Long story short Church and Turing showed there were limits to the ability of computers
不论时间再多 存储空间再大
no matter how much time or memory you have
总是有无法解决的问题
there are just some problems that cannot be solved ever.
丘奇和图灵共同努力确定了计算的局限
The concurrent efforts by Church and Turing to determine the limits of computation,
并且基本上形式化证明了可计算性 现在被称为丘奇-图灵论题
and in general, formalize computability, are now called the Church-Turing Thesis.
这时（1936年）图灵只有24岁，他的事业才刚刚开始
At this point in 1936 Turing was only 24 years old and really only just beginning his career.
1936年到1938年 他在普林斯顿读完了博士 导师是丘奇
From 1936 through 1938 he completed a PhD at Princeton University
毕业后图灵回到了剑桥
under the guidance of Church then after graduating he returned to Cambridge.
1939年刚果 英国被卷入了二战
Shortly after in 1939 Britain became embroiled in World War II,
图灵开始为战争出谋划策
Turing's genius was quickly applied to the war effort.
实际上 战争开始前一年
In fact a year before the war started
他就已经在英国政府密码学校兼职了
he was already working part-time at the UK's government Code and Cypher school
这个学校就是布莱切利园附近的一个密码破译组织
which was the British code breaking group based out of Bletchley Park.
图灵的一项主要工作是破译德军的通讯
One of his main efforts was figuring out how to decrypt German communications
尤其是使用enigma机器的通讯
especially those that use the enigma machine.
简单说这些机器的作用就是打乱文字
In short these machines scrambled text.
比如你输入字母 H-E-L-L-O 而输出结果是XWDBJ
Like you'd type the letters H-E-L-L-O and the letters XWDBJ would come out.
这个过程称为加密
This process is called encryption.
加密过程不是随机的
The scrambling wasn't random.
规则由enigma顶部一系列可重排的转子确定
The behavior was defined by a series of re-orderable rotors on the top
每个转子有26个旋转位置
of the enigma machine, each with 26 possible rotational positions.
机器正面还有一个插板
There was also a plug board at the front of the machine
能够完成两两字母交换
that allowed pairs of letters to be swapped.
总计有数十亿种设置
In total there were billions of possible settings.
如果你有一个enigma机，并且知道正确的转子和面板设置
If you had your own enigma machine and you knew the correct rotor and plug board settings
输入XWDBJ 你就可以得到"hello"
you could type in XWDBJ and hello would come out.
换句话说 你就破译了这条信息
In other words, you decrypted the message.
德军当然不会在公共网络上分享自己的enigma设置
Of course the German military wasn't sharing their enigma settings on Social Media
所以盟军必须破解这些密码
so the allies had to break the code.
考虑到转子和插板的组合之多
With billions of Rotor and plug board combinations
手工破译是不可能的
there was no way to check them all by hand.
图灵运气比较好
Fortunately for Turing,
enigma机及其使用者并非十全十美
Enigma machines and the people who operated them were not perfect,
比如一个字母编码后一定会改变
like one key flaw was that a letter would never be encoded as itself
所以h加密后绝对不会还是h
as in an h was never encrypted as an h.
图灵利用了这个缺陷 在波兰译码人员的工作基础上
Turing, building on earlier work by Polish code breakers,  designed a special-Purpose
设计了专用的机电式计算机 就是"炸弹机"
electro-mechanical computer called the Bombe that took advantage of this flaw.
给定一条加密后的消息 炸弹机会尝试各种加密组合
It tried lots and lots of combinations of enigma settings for a given encrypted message
如果它找到一种设置 其解密后的字母没有改变
If the Bombe found a setting that led to a letter being encoded as itself
我们知道真正的enigma机肯定不会这样 所以这个组合不成立
which we know the real Enigma machine couldn't do, that combination was discarded
然后机器继续计算下一个
then the machine moved on to try another combination.
于是炸弹机用于大幅缩减enigma机器设置的范围
So Bombes were used to greatly narrow the number of Possible enigma settings.
这样译码员只需要破译可能性最大的组合
This allowed human code breakers to hone their efforts on the most probable solutions
在解码后的信息中寻找常见的德语单词
looking for things like common german words in fragments of decoded text.
为避免密码被破译
Periodically the Germans would suspect someone was decoding their communications
德军会定期升级enigma机器
and upgrade the enigma machine
比如会增加一个转子 这样会新增更多组合
like they'd add another rotor creating many more combinations
甚至还会重新制造新的加密设备
they even built entirely new encryption machines.
整个战争期间 图灵和他布莱切利园的同事们
Throughout the war Turing and his colleagues at Bletchley Park
不知不倦的破译密码
worked tirelessly to defeat these mechanisms
总的来说 破译德军通讯获得的情报
and overall the intelligence gained from decrypted German communications
让盟军在许多情形下占得先机
gave the allies an edge in many theatres
甚至有历史学家说这些情报让战争提早了多年结束
with some historians arguing it shortened the war by years.
战后 图灵回到了学界
After the war Turing returned to Academia
参与了多个早期的电子计算机工作 比如曼彻斯特一号
and contributed to many early electronic computing efforts like the Manchester Mark 1
它是程序存储计算机的先驱 影响深远
which was an early and influential stored-Program computer.
但他在战后最著名的贡献在人工智能领域
But his most famous post-war contribution was to artificial intelligence,
这个领域太超前了 直到1956年才得名
a field so new that it didn't even get that name until 1956.
它的内容太多了 以后再说
It's a huge topic so we'll get to it again in future episodes.
1950年 图灵想象到了未来某一天、
In 1950 Turing could envision a future where computers were powerful enough
计算机功能极强 已经和人类的水平相当 或者至少无法区分计算机或人类
to exhibit intelligence equivalent to or at least indistinguishable from that of a human.
图灵提出当计算机可以让人类相信它并非机器的时候
Turing postulated that a computer would deserve to be called intelligent
计算机就拥有了智能
if it could deceive a human into believing that it was human.
这个假设成为了现在图灵测试的基础
This became the basis of a simple test now called the Turing Test.
想象你正和2个人在聊天
Imagine that you are having a conversation with two different people
不是面对面或通过语音 而是互相发送文字
not by voice or in person but by sending typed notes back and forth.
你可以问任何问题并得到回答
You can ask any questions you want and you get replies.
但是这2人中的1个其实是计算机
But one of those two people is actually a computer.
如果你不能确定哪个是人哪个是计算机
If you can't tell which one is human and which one is a computer
那么计算机就通过了测试
then the computer passes the test
有一个更现代版的测试
There's a modern version of this test called a Completely Automated Public Turing Test
CAPTCHA 俗称"验证码"
称为"全自动区分人类和计算机的公开图灵测试"，简称CAPTCHA
to tell computers and humans apart or CAPTCHA for short.
验证码在互联网很常见
These are frequently used on the internet
用于防止自动化系统在网站内发布垃圾信息
to prevent automated systems from doing things like posting spam on Websites.
不得不说 有时候我也看不懂那些歪歪扭扭的东西是什么
I'll admit sometimes I can't read what those squiggly things say.
这么说我也是计算机吗
Does that mean I'm a computer?
通常我们不会深入这些历史人物的私生活
Normally in this series we don't delve into the personal lives of these historical figures
但对图灵来说
But in Turing's case his name has been inextricably tied
这个名字与悲剧密不可分 因此不得不说
to tragedy so his story is worth mentioning.
图灵是同性恋
Turing was gay in a time when homosexuality was illegal
但那个时代 同性恋在英国以及世界绝大数地区是非法的
in the united Kingdom and much of the world.
1952年图灵家失窃 官方在调查中发现了图灵的性取向
An investigation into a 1952 Burglary at his home revealed his sexual orientation
随后官方以"严重猥亵"罪名起诉图灵
to the authorities who charged him with gross indecency.
图灵被判罪名成立 被迫接受监禁或
Turing was convicted and given a choice between imprisonment
保外就医(荷尔蒙疗法控制性欲)
or probation with hormonal treatments to suppress his sexuality.
他选择了后者 也是为了继续自己的学术生涯
He chose the latter in part to continue his academic work,
但荷尔蒙疗法改变了他的情绪和性格
but it altered his mood and personality
可能实际情况永远不得而知
Although the exact circumstances will never be known,
但现在公认图灵于1954年服毒自杀
it's most widely accepted that Alan Turing took his own life by poison in 1954.
时年41岁
He was only 41.
为了纪念他对计算机科学理论的贡献
Many things have been named in recognition of
许多东西都以他为名
Turing's contributions to theoretical computer science.
但最著名的要数图灵奖
But perhaps the most prestigious among them is the Turing Award
计算机科学领域的最高荣誉
the highest distinction in the field of computer science
相当于物理、化学和其他科学领域的诺贝尔奖
equivalent to a nobel prize in Physics, chemistry or other sciences.
尽管英年早逝 但图灵仍启发了第一代计算机科学家NDespite a life cut short Alan inspired the first generation of computer scientists
正由于他奠定了当今数字时代的基础 我们才得以享受
and laid key groundwork that enabled a digital era we get to enjoy today.
下周见
I'll see you next week.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@Auriance 校：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组